<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A civil correction of a sawcy impudent pamphlet, lately published, entituled, A brief account of the designs which the papists have had against the Earl of Shaftsbury, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20376</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885816</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204143</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240893770</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4364A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 714.i.8[6]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225026</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885816</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99885816e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20376)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; F1:2[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A civil correction of a sawcy impudent pamphlet, lately published, entituled, A brief account of the designs which the papists have had against the Earl of Shaftsbury, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>re-printed by the heirs of Andrew Anderson, printer to his most sacred Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Brief account of the designs which the papists have had against the Earl of Shaftsbury, occasioned by his commitment, July 2. 1681 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Anti-Catholicism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204143:1"/>
            <head>A Civil CORRECTION OF A Sawcy impudent PAMPHLET, Lately Published, Entituled, A Brief Account of the Designs which the <hi>Papists</hi> have had against the Earl of Shaftsbury, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAving very often heard of Popish Designs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Earl of <hi>Sh.</hi> but never being able to get any true account of 'em in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, it is not to be imagined how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly pleased I was the other day to meet with a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pamphlet, entituled, <hi>A brief Account of the Designs which the</hi> Papists <hi>have had against the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>occasioned by his Commitment,</hi> July 2. 1681. Very good, thought <hi>I,</hi> now the Mountain brings forth, or never: So with Hat over eyes, and Legs acrosse, very gravely to reading fell I. The first thing <hi>I</hi> meet withal, is indeed a very solid Position; Had Sir <hi>F. W.</hi> himself laboured and strained for a Period, o' my Conscience he could not have squeez'd out a duller. Says the worthy Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleteer, <hi>Though the Apprehending of the Right Honourable the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>hath filled the Town and Country with talk and noise, yet it neither frightens nor discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth any Protestant, or good</hi> English <hi>man.</hi> Well said old Tautology: That's as plain as the Nose in ones Face: Chear up my Country-men; for discouragment being the effect of fear, and fear the immediat cause of discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragment, there is nothing so evident, as that a man may be frightned, and not discouraged, or discouraged and not frightened: that is to say, a man may be frighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; not frightned neither. So much for Rhetorick. But prithee Sweet heart, since thou wilt be scribling, write Truth, though thou canst not afford us Sense. For the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending that Right Honourable Earl does frighten most true Protestants, &amp; good <hi>English</hi> men; For, if that Right Honourable Earl has been all along sovigorous an Asserter of the Protestant Religion, the Rights and Liberties of the Subject, the Laws of the Kingdom, and the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Prerogative of the Crown; Can it do less than strike astonishment into the heart and mind of every honest man, to find him accused of no less Crimes than <hi>High-Treason</hi> at last? The Conspiring to seize upon, and secure the King's Person by violence; the subverting the Government, and raising Men and Arms to that purpose. I believe it frightens most men, and that most men are something apt to apprehend, that he may not be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether so good a Protestant and Patriot as he would have us believe he was: If he be, we have reason to be afraid for his Innocency; if he be not, we have reason to be afraid that the best part of the Kingdom has long been miserably deceiv'd and misled, and to dread the Ruine into which he was seducing us. Therefore good <hi>Mr.</hi> Pamphleteer be pleas'd to recollect your self, and do not forestall the Justice of the Laws, that must acquit or condemn him; and let me moreover inform your worship of one thing, that if you are not frightened at my Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury's</hi> being apprehended for a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>I</hi> am sure you ought to be ashamed of your Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>As for Example: You are pleased to observe, That the Perjuries of Needy and Suborned Villains may bring troubles upon Innocency. Good Friend of mine, be tender how you treat the King's Witnesses: For if want be once urg'd as an Argument against the Validity of a Testimony, for ought <hi>I</hi> know there is not one Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit has been hang'd these three years, but may be as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a Traytor as the E. of S.</p>
            <p>But for a shrewd Argument let you alone, I'le war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you, <hi>(viz.) If he were traiterously inclined</hi> (you say) <hi>yet he is wiser than to communicat Designs of that Nature to such base and mercenary Rascals as are said to have witnessed against him, or to enter into a Conspiracy not only with beggarly Fellows, but with</hi> Irish <hi>men and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists.</hi> One part of this I'le grant you; He has not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into this Conspiracy with beggarly Fellows, <hi>Irish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> and Papists only; for (if rumour may be believ'd) there are a great many Rich <hi>Knaves</hi> in the Pack; Though (to return an Argument of your own upon you, and tickle you in the true <hi>Protestant</hi> place,) who so fit to be employed in Designs of that nature, as desperate beggarly Fellows and Villains? Now, if his Lordships Wisdom would not think <hi>Irish-men,</hi> (and Papists espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) Rogues enough to undertake the dethroning of the King, and subverting of the Government, he had a secret Complement for them in his heart, which I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid he'l hardly thank you for publishing. The time was (if your Protestant Pamphlets be all true) when <hi>Irish-men</hi> and Papists were not thought so very unfit to engage in Designs of that nature; Bu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <q xml:lang="lat">Qui color albus erat, nunc est Contrarius albo.</q> There's <hi>Latine</hi> for you, Brother Pamphleteer; by which Language of the Beast <hi>I</hi> suppose you'l not fail to find me for a <hi>Jesuit,</hi> next time you have a need to write again.</p>
            <p>But in the mean while, <hi>This Honourable Gentle-man</hi> (you say) <hi>is h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, whose whole tenour and universal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his Life have spoken him, not only a Person of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204143:2"/>greatest Abilities, but of the highest Loyalty to his Majesty, and warmest Zeal for His Service, that any these three Kingdoms have produced in this Age.</hi> Verily, Friend, the Truth is not in thee: For this Honourable Gentleman commanded a Regiment, that once with warmest Zeal sought against His Majesty; This Honourable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was He, that did his utmost to confirm the Usurper <hi>Cromwel</hi> in the Throne of His Majesty; This Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Gentleman was always a Member of that Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Authority that opposed His Majesty: And are not these (and be hang'd to you) Arguments of Loyalty to His Majesty? Look you Friend, if his Lordship can give no better Arguments of his Loyalty, when he comes to his Tryal than you do in your Panegyrick upon him, he may change to march up <hi>Tower-Hill</hi> for his Loyalty; and, for ought I know, the Trick he'l shew there may be the first good Service he ever did, or will do the Publick.</p>
            <p>If it were possible, thou Phamphleteer, I would be serious with thee, but thou art a sort of a Thing that hopest to word people out of their sense and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing; and by a trowling of Syllables one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in a gingling order, wouldst put off thy shallow incobaerent Nonsence, for matter of weight and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I have observed often in half judging Capacities, when thy know not well how to give an Account of what they have read, or may be, only heard; their us<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual way of passing their Censure is by gravely shaking the Noddle, and solidly noting there's a great deal in it: So it may be justly said of thy Pamphlet; There is indeed a great deal in't; but it is such stuff as once made up a certain Cardinal's Equipage, only Lumber and Filthyness, fiter for a Dunghil than any place else. Nay, canst thou be less than asham'd, thou Son of Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity! to wast the Paper Manufacture of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom at so unaccountable a Rate? 'Tis enough to breed a Dearth of Rags in the Nation; and if once that should happen, which way would'st thou contrive to hide thy Nakedness! Would the E. of S. do himself Justice, he ought to prosecute thee for a Libel upon him: For is it less than a Libel to praise him for his unwearied Cares and Endeavours to obviate the formidable Growth of <hi>France?</hi> Fie for shame, do the Honourable Gentleman Justice, and tell the World who it was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selled the breaking of the Triple League, and so by dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uniting the common Interest of the Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> made way for all the War and Desolation that has since follow'd amongst our Neighbours. If he (as you say) could not concur in Designs which he conceiv'd tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Ruin of these Kingdoms, and the endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Monarchy, as well as to the subversion of the Protestant Religion, both here and else-where, perswade him, if thou canst, to lay by the at least 30 Pardons which he has pass'd since his first Ministry, and put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self upon his Trial from that, to this present day of his Innocence. If to this Wise and Noble Peer's Influence (according to your observation) His Majesty owes the successful administration of his Affairs for many years together: tell us, if thou canst, what means the Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of so many Addresses from the last Parliaments, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrating from a long date the defects and miscarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages of the Government, and the Grievances that from thence have fallen upon the people? tell us who it was that caused the first shutting up of the Exchequer, to the distress of so many poor Widows and Orphans, whose All was lodged there? If the Friends and Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Arbitrariness and Popery at home, are become his implacable and profess'd Enemies, prithee tell us, if possible, how long it is since they first fell out? Was it before he would have brought all Elections for Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to have been decided in the Court of Chancery, and so have robb'd the House of Commons of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est and most tutelar Priviledges they ever enjoy'd, or was it since? Rather, was it the goodness of our Just and Gracious King, that could not be prevailed upon by him to make so cruel an intrenchment upon the Rights and Safety of his People; that caus'd this Noble Earl to withdraw himself from the Affairs of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, or not? Oh Truth! Truth! how hast thou been muzzl'd! But to proceed.</p>
            <p>My Author's Worship is pleased (in his remark of the Seals being taken from this Honourable Earl) to observe, <hi>That when.</hi> They <hi>found that</hi> They <hi>could find neither Ambition, nor Covetousness in him, to impress and work upon, so as to bring him to</hi> Their <hi>Lure, that then</hi> They <hi>accosted him with such tenders of Greatness, Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Wealth, as few but him would have had the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Self denial and Uprightness to refuse. In</hi> the name of Nonsense, what would this Laborious Bombastick Fool mean by his <hi>Impress,</hi> his <hi>Lure,</hi> and his <hi>Accost?</hi> Here's the taking the Seals from him, on purpose to give him good words, to bring him to their Lure: A very plotick fetch! What stuff is this to perswade any reasonable understanding withal! Oh, but <hi>I</hi> had almost forgot; there is the word <hi>They</hi> to season the Carrion with, <hi>viz. When</hi> They found, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And again, <hi>They accosted him.</hi> Now this <hi>Aenigmatical</hi> Ass would have us believe there is a great deal of meaning in that word <hi>They:</hi> That is, having mentioned the popish party with scandal before, he would now joyn the King with 'em too; For who else can take away the Seals from a Chancellor? Or who else could accost him (as he calls it) with tenders of Greatness and Honour? So that here is no less than the King implicitely reflected on, as a Favourer of <hi>Popery,</hi> to affirm which, is Treason by the known Laws of the Land; and from thence <hi>I</hi> appeal to every true Subject of <hi>England,</hi> if a Cause thus defended, can, or ought to be thought well of.</p>
            <p>The rest of the page is fill'd up with a long impertinent story of a Design to accuse this Earl of Treason; that one Collonel <hi>Conquest</hi> was to have been his Accuser; that all the Offices wherein he had been concern'd were sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; and that They greatly reckon'd upon the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> as admirably moulded for their businesse, for the Fear many of 'em might have of losing their Pensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at the end of the Sessions. Admirably well express'd upon my Life! This Rogue would, by his good will, make that <hi>House of Commons</hi> a Cake of wey Dough: Moui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for their business! Very quaint truly! But here is he at it again with his old <hi>They: They</hi> greatly reckon'd upon the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> as obliged by their Pensions: Now, who can be esteemed to expect any thing from a Pensioner, for fear of losing his Pension, but he that gives him his pension? So that here the Villain is throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dirt again in the King's Face; as if that were the only way to get clear his filthy Patron. Here would he knavishly insinuate a scandalous Interpretation of the Kings Goodness, which ought to be no more questioned than limited by the hands of a Subject, here is his Nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle itching to make the world believe, That these pensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners (as he calls them) were meerly bought by the King for indirect and underhand-services, when upon a just and impartial scrutiny, it will easily appear, that those Gentlemen were either such, whose Estates and Fortunes had been impar'd in the Service of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Father, that Royal Martyr of ever Blessed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and that way gave them pretence to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty's Largesse and Bounty; or else others who from their former Delinquency, had return'd with Penitence into the Mercy and Service of their Master, and that way became Partakers of his Liberality, that they might (if possible) be never more led away, by their wants or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204143:2"/>ambition, into those Courses that ruin'd the Kingdom before, and enslav'd us under the heavy Yoak of an Usurper. But I am glad to find the Cause, now it is shaken, thus dis-embogue it self, and hope it will open the eyes of every honest <hi>English</hi>-man, to have his heart and his hands ready to defend the King, his Honour and Authority from all the vile wicked Designs, and undermining Mischiefs that have been contriving and hatching against him; And how far the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>S.</hi> may have been that way concern'd, I think may, in some measure, be guess'd at, from the stile and matter of the Defence, which this miserable Scribler has the impudence to make for him.</p>
            <p>Next, to wind up the bottom of this foolish relation, he is pleased to pass a Complement upon the Kings Council, for wanting at that time sufficient matter to Accuse him of; and so proceeds forward to his <hi>They</hi> once more; and tells us, how <hi>They</hi> having miscarried in their Attempts upon the E's life, change the Scheme of their Designs, (good Lord what fine words are here) and lay a Plot to blast his Reputation: And who, says he, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o fit for this work, as the Ecclesiasticks, as being in a more Implicit Obedince to <hi>Them.</hi> So I am glad I have got you here good Mr. <hi>Pamphleteero!</hi> Who are the Ecclesiaticks and the posse of the Clergy (as you are pleased to term it) reasonably to be thought most obedient to, but the Head of the Church? So here the King is shuffled in amongst your <hi>They</hi> again: Then you tell us, the Pulpits instead of commending Jesus Christ to the Consciences of men, were employ'd through all parts of the Nation in Blasting the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>S.</hi> And (if all be true) it had not been much amiss if it had been so, for it is requisite in Preaching (after the Praises of God) to arm mens Souls against the practices of the Devil. Though it is evident, that your Worshipful Dulness lies in this point most abominably, and I dare be hang'd (as you deserve) could the matter be enquired into, if ever (since <hi>Hugh Peter's</hi> his time) any one of the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>S.</hi> Names, has been so much as mentioned in a Pulpit; by which, and what went before, it is easily to be perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you are neither a Friend to the King, nor the Church; and what Party you belong to then, I leave every Honest Impartial man to Judge according to his Conscience.</p>
            <p>But now I think better of the matter; What Splee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick Fool but my self would take the pains to bestow an answer upon this Dunce, this <hi>True Protestant,</hi> as he calls himself! If he be a <hi>Round-head,</hi> a <hi>Rumper,</hi> a Rebel of Old <hi>Jack Presbyter's</hi> Stamp, why is he ashamed of his Title? Why does he Cloak his Schism under the Name of <hi>True Protestant?</hi> for we know no True Protestant here, but such as are so according to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is Established by Law: For if every one that Protests against Popery, be a True Protestant; for ought I perceive, the Great <hi>Turk</hi> has as much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to that Title as any body. That this Vermine then is not of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is easily to be conjectured by this treatment of its Clergy: That he is not an over good Subject, is apparent enough by the Company he has found out for the King; yet this is he that dares defend the cause of a man, under an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation of the most detestable Treason in the World, exhibited against him by several Witensses, whose worth and Validity none once so zealous to defend and justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie as the Earl himself and his Party were, though now they have the misfortune, to fall under our Authours displeasure, and to be treated with no better Titles, <hi>Then Beggarly fellows, Indigent, Mercenary and Perjur'd Rascals, Beggarly Rascals, such as have acknowledged that they are Hired to Swear what they have done,</hi> &amp;c. Now to do the World Justice, and to do the Laws Justice, which 'tis to be hop'd will do the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>S.</hi> Justice; let us enquire, who these Beggarly Rascals are that were hired to Swear what they have done.</p>
            <p>In the first place, <hi>Heyns</hi> so much talk'd-of of late (as report tells us) is one of those who has a large share in the Charge against this Noble E. Good <hi>Mr. Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleteero,</hi> is he a Beggarly Perjur'd Rascal? I believe my <hi>L. S.</hi> will not take it very well at your hands to treat his old Friend and Acquaintance so coursly; for such he once was certainly, else, why did he and several Lords more Petition for a Blank Pardon for him some few Weeks since, under the Title of a man of Quality and unquestionable Reputation? One that could give a farther account of the Popish Plot then any had been discovered yet? Was he then a Beggar? Was he then Perjur'd? No, I believe neither; for suppose the Party were so Charitable to keep him from Begging, and the Kings Wisdom in not granting him a Pardon has kept him from being Perjur'd.</p>
            <p>As for the other Witnesses against this Noble Peer, I believe it will be for your Credit, as soon as you can, to retract your Reflections upon them too. For if their Credit is not sufficient, as you say, to suport such a Charge against such a Peer of <hi>England</hi> as the E. of S. is Committed for; How came it about, that some of 'em were once thought fitting, even by that Earl himself, to support as great a Charge against several other Peers of <hi>England,</hi> (some whereof are still Prisoners in the <hi>Tower</hi>) equal in Honour, and for ought I know Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in Honesty to your E. of S.</p>
            <p>But some of these Witnesses you are pleased to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, have acknowledged themselves Hired to Swear what they have done; handle that point as you love your Cause with Caution: I am afraid it will not be for your Earls advantage, when it comes to be known who it was Hired them to Swear what they have done.</p>
            <p>If this will not do, what think you of a Dying Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <hi>Fitz-Harris?</hi> His Solemn Declaration at his Death Signed and Attested by unquestionable Hands? Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by his own last Speech at the Gallowes in every particular Article to be true? If he was ever before thought a sufficient Witness against the <hi>Queen,</hi> the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Denby,</hi> &amp;c. Sure at his Death, under the awe of a terrifi'd Conscience, in the last Agonies of Contrition and Repentance, he may be allow'd to speak Truth of a L. H. and E. of S.</p>
            <p>That he was thought a sufficient Witness before; I appeal to that worthy Grand Jury, who (upon his single Information only, though then a Prisoner, just coming upon his Tryal for the Treason which he has suffer'd for since) thought fit to find a Bill of Murder against the Earl of <hi>Denby,</hi> as concern'd in the Death of Justice <hi>Godfrey.</hi> Nay he was thought so good, so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and so necessary a Witness, that all the Arts of Corruption and all the Tricks of Wrested Law, were made use of by the Faction to save him; Jurles were packt, that by their proceeding, seem'd to have as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel Conscience; as the <hi>Hamburgh</hi> Sheriff that returned them had Loyalty. Insolent Advocates were found out for him, to threaten the Judges in their Office, and if it were possible, to make the Sword of Justice tremble in the Honest hand that held it; but it was kept steady, to the Immortal Honour of that Glorious Judge; who when the History of this Age, shall be written, cannot but be remember'd as one of the first Protectors and Supporters of <hi>Englands</hi> threatn'd Monarchy and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>These things then being granted (as they must be) that the Evidence of these men against this Earl, or any body else, ought to have as much weight and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, as against any other Subject in the Kingdom; and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204143:3"/>that they have been heard with Credit against di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Subjects of the Kingdom, is manifest: How comes it to pass upon an Indictment preferr'd the last Sessions at the <hi>Old-Bayly</hi> against one <hi>Stephen Colledge</hi> for High Treason, there Swore positively against him, by six several Witnesses, that the Grand-Jury could fail to find the Bill? When at the same Court, not long ago, upon the bare Testimony of one man, they found an Indictment of Recusancy against the Duke of <hi>York;</hi> Shall the first Prince of the Blood be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon the slender and doubtful Testimony of one Witness? And shall not six be enough to make good a Charge against a Wretched <hi>Joyner,</hi> a Profligate Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Fellow, that has been for these three years ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of as a Common Asperser of the Government, and a sower of Sedition amongst the People? <hi>I</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all the World if this be common Justice! The cause of this can be nothing less, then the miserable decay of all fear of Heaven, and Reverence of Vertue amongst us; when we see men entrusted with Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Power, administring the severest Cruelty with one hand, and stopping the Justice of it with the other: Nothing can redeem us from this, but earnest and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Prayers to the Almighty Spirit of Truth, to assist &amp; de fendus, whilst we make an early &amp; resolute appeal to our Gracious Soveraign, to interpose with his Authority, and restore us to the Security of our Liberties, that the Laws may be turn'd again into their due Course and Channel, that power may be no more entrusted in the hands of such men, as practise the abuse of into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowing of all Justice, the destruction of all Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Unity amongst us, the encouragement of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery and Falshood, the Stifling of Truth, the Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Innocence, and the confusion of our general Safety.</p>
            <closer>God save the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Re-printed by the Heirs of <hi>Andrew Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> Printer to his most Sacred Majesty, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>